Elizabeth Gurley Flynn: Joe Hill Case Materials TAM.529
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn: Joe Hill Case Materials
1915
TAM.529
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.25 linear feet (1 Box)
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn (1890-1964) was a leading Irish-American Communist, socialist, feminist, labor organizer, orator, and campaigner for civil liberties. Joe Hill (1879-1915), labor songwriter and member of the Industrial Workers of the World, was convicted of murder after a politically charged trial and executed by the State of Utah on November 19, 1915. The collection contains prison letters to Flynn, a letter to William D. Haywood, Hill’s “My Last Will” (a poem), letters from defense attorney O. N. Hilton, lyrics of a song by Hill for Flynn’s son, Fred (“To Bronco Buster Flynn"), a clippings scrapbook about the case, “Joe Hill Murdered,” and a memorial program.
Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This collection was separated from Communist Party of the United States of America Records (TAM 132). The accession number 2006.072 is associated with this collection. The Communist Party, USA Records were donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by the Communist Party, USA in the summer of 2006. The records were part of a larger donation that included the library of the Reference Center for Marxist Studies, the photo morgue of the Daily Worker and Daily World, and approximately 76 linear feet of audiovisual materials.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains prison letters to Flynn, a letter to William D. Haywood, Hill’s “My Last Will” (a poem), letters from defense attorney O. N. Hilton, lyrics of a song by Hill for Flynn’s son, Fred (“To Bronco Buster Flynn’), a clippings scrapbook about the case, “Joe Hill Murdered,” and an undated theatre memorial program from Leipzig, Germany.
Historical/Biographical Note
Elizabeth Gurley Flynn (1890-1964) was a leading Irish-American Communist, socialist, feminist, labor organizer, orator, and campaigner for civil liberties. Joe Hill (1879-1915), labor songwriter and member of the Industrial Workers of the World (many of his songs appear in the IWW Songbook), was convicted of murder after a politically charged trial and executed by the State of Utah on November 19, 1915.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically in one series.
Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Haywood, Big Bill, 1869-1928. -- |v Portraits; Hill, Joe, 1879-1915; Hilton, O. N.--Portraits.; Industrial Workers of the World.; Correspondence.; Poetry.; Scrapbooks.; Trials (Political crimes and offenses) |z United States.
- Series I: Joe Hill Case Materials, 1915
  - Hill, Joe: "Dear Judge" (signed letter), Oct 20, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Hill, Joe: Memorial Program, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hill, Joe: "My Last Will" (poem), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hill, Joe: Prison Letters to E. G. Flynn (originals), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hill, Joe: Prison Letters to E. G. Flynn (photostats), 1915 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hill, Joe: Prison Letter to William D. Haywood, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Hill, Joe: Telegram to E. G. Fynn, Nov 18, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Hill, Joe: "To Bronco Buster Flynn" (song lyrics), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hilton, O. N.: Letters to Hill, Flynn, Judge, Board of Pardons, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Hilton, O. N.: Telegram to E. G. Flynn, Nov 20, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Joe Hill Case: Letters to/from Third Parties, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Joe Hill: Der Mann Niemals Starb (Theatre program, Leipzig), undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook: "Joe Hill Murdered", 1915 (Box 1, Folder 13)